This story
هذه القصة عن
is about taking imagination seriously.
أخذ المخيلة على محمل الجد
Fourteen years ago,
منذ 14 عاماً
I first encountered this ordinary material, fishnet,
تعرفت على المواد الطبيعية المشكلة لشبكات الصيد
used the same way for centuries.
وهي نفسها التي تستخدم منذ قرون
Today, I'm using it to create
اليوم .. انا استخدمها لكي أصنع
permanent, billowing, voluptuous forms
اشكال " حسية - دائمة - متمايزة "
the scale of hard-edged buildings
بأحجام المباني الكبيرة
in cities around the world.
في المدن حول العالم
I was an unlikely person to be doing this.
في الحقيقة انا لست الشخص المؤهل لذلك
I never studied sculpture,
فانا لم ادرس صناعة النحت
engineering or architecture.
والهندسة المدنية ولا الهندسة المعمارية
In fact, after college
في الحقيقة .. بعد دراستي الجامعية
I applied to seven art schools
قدمت طلبات دخول لسبع مدارس فنية
and was rejected by all seven.
وتم رفضي من قبل السبع
I went off on my own to become an artist,
فاعتمدت على نفسي لكي اكمل مسيرتي الفنية
and I painted for 10 years,
لقد رسمت لنحو عشر سنوات
when I was offered a Fulbright to India.
وذات يوم عرض علي رحلة الى الهند
Promising to give exhibitions of paintings,
بعد وعد بان ان تقام عدة معارض للوحاتي
I shipped my paints and arrived in Mahabalipuram.
فارسلت اللوحات بالشحن وذهبت انا الى "ماهاباليبرام"
The deadline for the show arrived --
واقترب موعد العرض
my paints didn't.
ولم تصل اللوحات
I had to do something.
وكان يجب علي ان اقدم شيئا
This fishing village was famous for sculpture.
وكانت قرية الصيادين تلك مشهورة بالمجسمات الفنية
So I tried bronze casting.
فحاولت ان استخدم البرونز لصناعة احدها ..
But to make large forms was too heavy and expensive.
ولكن كان ذلك صعباً ومكلفاً وكبيراً
I went for a walk on the beach,
فأخذت اسير على الشاطىء لعلي اجد فكرة ما
watching the fishermen
وانا اراقب الصيادين
bundle their nets into mounds on the sand.
وهم يسحبون شباك صيدهم نحو الشاطىء الرملي
I'd seen it every day,
لقد رايت ذلك المشهد ربما يوميا هناك
but this time I saw it differently --
ولكن تلك المرة كانت مختلفة
a new approach to sculpture,
فقد تراءت لي فكرة جديدة عن صنع المجسامات
a way to make volumetric form
مجسمات فراغية الشكل
without heavy solid materials.
بدون استخدام مواد ثقيلة
My first satisfying sculpture
كان مجسمي الاول " المقنع "
was made in collaboration with these fishermen.
صنع بمساعدة هولاء الصيادين
It's a self-portrait
انه مجسم يعبر عن نفسه
titled "Wide Hips."
اسميته " الارداف العريضة "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We hoisted them on poles to photograph.
ثم رفعته على أعمدة من اجل تصويره
I discovered
واكتشفت كم هو
their soft surfaces
مرن وناعم سطحه ..
revealed every ripple of wind
وكيف يتجاوب مع كل نسمة هواء
in constantly changing patterns.
وتتمايز اشكاله
I was mesmerized.
لقد فتنت به
I continued studying craft traditions
استمريت بدراسة الحرف
and collaborating with artisans,
بالتعاون مع المصممين
next in Lithuania with lace makers.
في لتوانيا وصناع " الدانتيل "
I liked the fine detail
لقد احببت التفاصيل الصغيرة
it gave my work,
لقد اعطت لعملي معناه ..
but I wanted to make them larger --
ولكني اريد ان اصنع مجسمات اكبر
to shift from being an object you look at
اريد ان انتقل من مرحلة شيء تنظر اليه
to something you could get lost in.
الى شيء تضيع في طياته
Returning to India to work with those fishermen,
وبالعودة الى الهند للعمل مع الصيادين
we made a net
صنعنا في البداية شبكة ..
of a million and a half hand-tied knots --
من مليون ونصف المليون عقدة يدوية
installed briefly in Madrid.
تم تركيبها في مدريد لفترة
Thousands of people saw it,
وشاهدها الآلاف
and one of them was the urbanist
كان منهم مخطط مدن
Manual Sola-Morales
يدعى مانويل سولا موراليس
who was redesigning the waterfront
وكان قد صمم واجهة بحرية
in Porto, Portugal.
في بورتو . البرتغال
He asked if I could build this
وسئلني ان اكنت استطيع ان ابني هذه
as a permanent piece for the city.
كمجسم دائم لمدينة
I didn't know if I could do that
لم اكن اعرف ان كان ذلك ممكنا
and preserve my art.
أن اقدم فني
Durable, engineered, permanent --
بصورة مهندسة دائمة قائمة
those are in opposition
انها عكس الصفات الموجودة في مجسماتي
to idiosyncratic, delicate and ephemeral.
الناعمة المؤقتة الضعيفة
For two years, I searched for a fiber
لعامين بحثت عن نوع من الاقمشة
that could survive ultraviolet rays,
يمكنه ان يصمد امام الاشعة الفوق بنفسجية
salt, air, pollution,
والرطوبة المالحة والتلوث
and at the same time remain soft enough
وبان يكون في ذات الوقت ناعما بما فيه الكفاية
to move fluidly in the wind.
لكي يتحرك بسلاسة مع الرياح
We needed something to hold the net up
واحتجنا شيئاً لكي نعلق عليه الشبكة
out there in the middle of the traffic circle.
في منتصف دوار مروري
So we raised this 45,000-pound steel ring.
اذا قمنا برفع حلقة معدنية بوزن 45 الف رطل
We had to engineer it
وقد صممت
to move gracefully in an average breeze
لكي تتحرك بصورة مقبولة ضمن الحدود المطلوبة
and survive in hurricane winds.
ولكي تصمد امام رياح الاعاصير
But there was no engineering software
ولكن لم يكن هناك برنامج حاسوبي
to model something porous and moving.
يمكنه ان يولد نموذج لشيء يتحرك وفي نفس الوقت " مسامي " - الشبكة -
I found a brilliant aeronautical engineer
لقد تعرفت على مهندس طيران مميز
who designs sails for America's Cup racing yachts
كان قد صمم الاشرعة لسباق اليخوت الامريكية
named Peter Heppel.
اسمه بيتير هيبيل
He helped me tackle the twin challenges
وقد ساعدني في تجاوز معوقتين
of precise shape
الشكل المحدد
and gentle movement.
والحركة المرنة
I couldn't build this the way I knew
فهذا المجسم لايمكن ان يبنى بطريقتي المعهودة
because hand-tied knots
بربط العقد يدويا
weren't going to withstand a hurricane.
فذلك لن يصمد امام الاعاصير
So I developed a relationship
لذا قمنا باستحداث اسلوب
with an industrial fishnet factory,
بالتعاون مع مصانع شبكات الصيد
learned the variables of their machines,
وبالاعتماد على آلاتهم المتعددة
and figured out a way
استطعنا ان نخرج بطريقة
to make lace with them.
لكي نستخدمها في صناعة المجسم
There was no language
ولم يكن هنالك طريقة
to translate this ancient, idiosyncratic handcraft
لكي ننقل الحرفة القديمة الغريبة
into something machine operators could produce.
الى آلة منتجة حديثة
So we had to create one.
لذا قمنا باستحداث آلة جديدة
Three years and two children later,
وبعد ثلاث سنوات من العمل انجبت بهما طفلين
we raised this 50,000-square-foot lace net.
استطعنا ان نشكل شبكة بمساحة 50 الف متر مربع
It was hard to believe
كان من الصعب ان أصدق
that what I had imagined
ان ما تخيلته
was now built, permanent
قد بني الآن وقد غدا مجسماً دائماً
and had lost nothing in translation.
دون ان يفقد اي شيء من بريق الماضي ومن نقل العملية الى الآلات الحديثة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This intersection had been bland and anonymous.
لقد كان الدوار المروري مجهول وباهت
Now it had a sense of place.
ولكن اليوم اصبح معلماً
I walked underneath it
لقد سرت اسفل المجسم
for the first time.
للمرة الاولى
As I watched the wind's choreography unfold,
شاهدت مداعبة نسائم الرياح خيوطه
I felt sheltered
لقد شعرت بالآمان
and, at the same time,
وفي نفس الوقت
connected to limitless sky.
شعرت بالاتصال بالسماء الممتدة
My life was not going to be the same.
ومنذ ذاك الحين تغيرت حياتي
I want to create these oases of sculpture
لقد رغبت بان اشرع في صناعة هذه المجسمات
in spaces of cities around the world.
في ساحات المدن حول العالم
I'm going to share two directions
وسوف اشارككم باثنين منها
that are new in my work.
وهم احدث مجسمين من اعمالي
Historic Philadelphia City Hall:
هنا في قاعة التاريخ في مجلس مدينة فيلديلفيا
its plaza, I felt, needed a material for sculpture
انها ساحة عامة .. شعرت بوجوب استخدام مادة
that was lighter than netting.
ادق من خيوط شبكة الصيد
So we experimented
لقد طبقنا تجربة باستخدام
with tiny atomized water particles
جزيئات صغيرة من الماء
to create a dry mist
لكي نصنع رذاذ جاف
that is shaped by the wind
ذاته الذي يتشكل من الرياح
and in testing, discovered
وفي الاختبار اكتشفنا
that it can be shaped by people
انه يمكن ان يتشكل - الرذاذ الجاف -
who can interact and move through it without getting wet.
ويتفاعل مع الاشخاص دون ان يرطبهم
I'm using this sculpture material
وقد استخدمت هذا الاسلوب بصناعة مجسم
to trace the paths of subway trains above ground
يتعقب خطوط مترو الانفاق من على سطح الارض
in real time --
على نحو لحظي
like an X-ray of the city's circulatory system unfolding.
وكانه " فحص باشعة اكس " للخطوط المواصلات الارضية
Next challenge,
التحدي التالي
the Biennial of the Americas in Denver
كان في بينيال في دينفر في امريكا
asked, could I represent
لقد طلب مني ان اقدم
the 35 nations of the Western hemisphere and their interconnectedness
مجسم يعبر عن 35 دولة غربية
in a sculpture?
في مجسم واحد
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I didn't know where to begin,
لم اكن اعرف كيفية البدء بذلك
but I said yes.
ولكني قلت نعم موافقة على التحدي
I read about the recent earthquake in Chile
لقد قرأت عن الهزة الارضية التي ضربت التشيلي مؤخراً
and the tsunami that rippled across
وكيف ان موجة التسونامي انتشرت على كامل
the entire Pacific Ocean.
المحيط الاطلسي
It shifted the Earth's tectonic plates,
وكيف غيرت من وضعية اللوحات التكتونية
sped up the planet's rotation
مما سرع دوران الكرة الارضية
and literally shortened the length of the day.
وقصر من زمن يومنا
So I contacted NOAA,
لذا فقد اتصلت بالهيئة الوطنية للمحيطات والغلاف الجوي
and I asked if they'd share their data on the tsunami,
وطلبت منهم مشاركتي بمعلومات التسونامي
and translated it into this.
وقد حولتها الى هذا الشكل
Its title: "1.26"
لقد اسميته 1.26
refers to the number of microseconds
انه عدد النقص في الميكرو ثانية
that the Earth's day was shortened.
الذي نقص منه يومنا على الكرة الارضية
I couldn't build this with a steel ring, the way I knew.
لم يمكن من الممكن بناء هذا المجسم بحلقة معدينة
Its shape was too complex now.
لان الشكل كان معقدا جدا
So I replaced the metal armature
لذا استبدلت الحديد
with a soft, fine mesh
بنوع معقد وناعم من الاقمشة
of a fiber 15 times stronger than steel.
وهو اقوى ب 15 مرة من الفولاذ
The sculpture could now be entirely soft,
لقد اصبح المجسم الآن باكلمه " ناعم ومرن "
which made it so light
وخفيف جداً
it could tie in to existing buildings --
ويمكن ربطه بالمبنى الاساسي
literally becoming part of the fabric of the city.
واصبح " حرفيا " جزء من نسج المدينة الكلي
There was no software
ولم يكن هناك برنامج
that could extrude these complex net forms
يمكنه ان يعزل و يدرس كل تلك الشبكات المعقدة
and model them with gravity.
ويشكلهم ويدرسهم تبعا للجاذبية الارضية
So we had to create it.
لذا صنعنا برنامج لتلك الغاية
Then I got a call from New York City
ومن ثم اتصل بي احد من مدينة نيويورك
asking if I could adapt these concepts
يتسائلون ان كان من الممكن تطبيق الامر ذاته في
to Times Square
ساحة "تايم سكوير"
or the High Line.
او في الطرق السريعة
This new soft structural method
ان المجسمات الناعمة
enables me to model these
تمكنني من تشكيل هذه الامور
and build these sculptures
وان ابني هذه المجسمات
at the scale of skyscrapers.
والتي هي بحجم ناطحات سحاب
They don't have funding yet,
ليس لديهم التمويل بعد
but I dream now
ولكن لدي حلم
of bringing these to cities around the world
بان ابني مجسمات كتلك في المدن حول العالم
where they're most needed.
في الاماكن التي تحتاجها
Fourteen years ago,
منذ 14 عاماً
I searched for beauty
كنت ابحث عن الجمال
in the traditional things,
في الامور التراثية
in craft forms.
في الحرف اليدوية
Now I combine them with hi-tech materials and engineering
والآن انا ادمج المواد عالية التقنية والهندسة
to create voluptuous, billowing forms
لكي اصنع اشكال مميزة ذات طابع حسي
the scale of buildings.
باحجام كبيرة كاحجام المباني
My artistic horizons continue to grow.
ان نطاق فني يتسع
I'll leave you with this story.
وسوف اختم مع هذه القصة
I got a call from a friend in Phoenix.
لقد جائني اتصال من صديق في فينكس
An attorney in the office
يقول ان محامي في المكتب
who'd never been interested in art,
لا يهتم بالفن على الاطلاق
never visited the local art museum,
ولم يزر يوما متحفاً او معرضاُ فنياً
dragged everyone she could from the building
اصر على ان ينزل الجميع من المبنى
and got them outside to lie down underneath the sculpture.
وان يخرجوا ويستلقوا اسفل هذا المجسم
There they were in their business suits,
لقد استلقوا ببدلاتهم الرسمية
laying in the grass,
على العشب
noticing the changing patterns of wind
لكي يشاهدوا تجاوب المجسم مع نسيم الهواء
beside people they didn't know,
بجانب اشخاص ربما لا يعرفونهم
sharing the rediscovery of wonder.
لكي يتشاركوا سوية إعادة اكتشاف عجائب الكون
Thank you.
شُكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you.
شُكراً.شُكراً
Thank you.
شُكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)